Nautilus (Submarine) Photograph Collection 1931 Mss.Ms.Coll.101
American Philosophical Society
Nautilus (Submarine) Photograph Collection
1931
Mss.Ms.Coll.101
American Philosophical Society
0.5 Linear feet
In 1931, the Nautilus, an O-12 class submarine, was fitted out to undertake an expedition to gather meteorological and oceanographical information while venturing beneath polar ice floes to the north pole. Although the crew did gather some useful information, the expedition was fated to suffer delays, accidents, and perhaps even sabotage. Although mechanical problems ruined any hope of reaching the pole, by late August, 1931, the Nautilus had maneuvered to the edge of the Arctic ice cap and was able to dive beneath a few floes. On its return, however, damage from storms and engine failure led the crew to scuttle the ship a few miles off the coast of Bergen, Norway. The Nautilus Collection is comprised of approximately 60 photographs, plus assorted newspaper clippings, postcards, and a few other miscellaneous items. The photographs document the voyage of the Nautilus from Camden, New Jersey, to the Brooklyn Naval Yard, and New London, Connecticut, across the Atlantic to the Arctic regions. The collection includes formal and informal photographs of the submarine, its interior, and ice floes, along with portraits of many of the ship's officers.
Bibliography
Casarini-Wadham, Maria Pia, By Submarine to the Arctic: Sir Hubert Wilkins' Nautilus Expedition of 1931 (Cambridge: Scott Polar Research Institution, University of Cambridge, 1989).
Grierson, John, Sir Hubert Wilkins; Enigma of Exploration (London: Robert Hale, 1960).
Thomas, Lowell, Sir Hubert Wilkins, His World of Adventure: An Autobiography Recounted to Lowell Thomas (London: Arthur Barker, 1962).
Wilkins, George Hubert, Under the North Pole: the Wilkins-Ellsworth Submarine Expedition (N.Y.: Brewer, Warren, and Putnam, 1931).
Naval History Note
Students of naval history, in particular those with an interest in submarine development and exploration, may find this collection of benefit.
Crew Manifest
The names of the participants are listed in a letter dated October 25, 1932, sent by Sir Hubert Wilkins to Brewer, Warren and Putnam Inc., the publishers of his book Under the North Pole. Additional information has been taken from the New York Times and New York American.
The list is in alphabetical order.
Frank Arthur O. Blumberg Chief Electrician Complete voyage
Edward Clark Quartermaster Complete voyage
Frank Crilley Master Diver Complete voyage
Sloan Danenhower Commander Complete voyage
Emile Dored Photographer Norway to end of voyage
Raymond W. Drakio Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
Jacob Fleutsch Mess boy Complete voyage
Willard I. Grimmer Assistant Radio Engineer Philadelphia to New York
Clarence D. Holland Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
John R. Janson Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
Siguard Johnson Ship's Carpenter Philadelphia to Norway
John H. Lundbeck Assistant Electrician Philadelphia to Norway
Ray E. Meyers Chief Radio Operator Complete voyage
Oliver C. Riggs First Assistant Engineer Philadelphia to England
Harry Rothschild Cook Philadelphia to Norway
Cornelius P. Royster Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
Isaac Schlossback Lieut-Commander Complete voyage
H. Carl Schnetter Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
Ralph D. Shaw Chief Engineer Complete voyage
Floyd M. Soule First Assistant Scientist Norway to end of voyage
H. Stakarov No information available England to end of Voyage
Emil Stamness Replacement Cook Norway to end of voyage
Dr. Harold U. Sverdrup Chief Scientist Norway to end of voyage
Dr. Bernhard Villinger Physician and Second Assistant Scientist Norway to end of voyage
Harry Zoller Assistant Engineer Complete voyage
Related Archival Materials note
A web exhibit based on the Nautilus Collection is available at http://www.amphilsoc.org/library/exhibits/nautilus/.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Donated by Mr. and Mrs. Ben B. Levitt, August 1, 1998. The scrapbook was compiled by Mrs. Arthur O. Blumberg (Accession #1998-2200 ms).
Scope and Contents note
The majority of items contained in the Nautilus Polar Expedition Collection are photographs of the submarine and crew at various stages during the submarine's fateful arctic expedition of 1931. These images are primarily press photographs accompanied by wire service captions. In each folder, a photocopy of each image precedes the original, with captions copied on the back. Other images come from the personal collection of Frank Blumberg, Chief Electrician aboard the Nautilus, and include snapshots and signed portraits. Finally, the collection also contains a scrapbook compiled by Blumberg from magazine clippings and photographs.
Biographical/Historical note
In 1931, Sir Hubert Wilkins undertook a scientific research mission to the North Pole using a modified O-class submarine leased from the United States Navy. The goals of this expedition were two-fold: to conduct scientific experiments and observations while moored to ice floes and while under way; and to successfully navigate to the North Pole while submerged beneath the Arctic ice floes. The experiments ranged from meteorological observations to temperature and water samples taken from the surface and the sea floor.
The submarine used was the O-12 (SS 73), built in 1916 by the Lake Torpedo Boat Co. of Bridgeport, CT. Commissioned in 1918, the boat spent most of her military career attached to Submarine Division 1, based at Coco Solo, Panama Canal Zone. O-12 displaced 566 tons submerged (491 tons surfaced), had a length of 175 ft., could reach speeds of 11 knots submerged (14 knots surfaced), and carried a crew of 29. She was decommissioned on June 17, 1924, and placed in reserve at the Philadelphia Navy Yard. After being transferred to the United States Shipping Board in 1930, Wilkins signed a lease for the use of the O-12 on February 1, 1931, at a cost of one dollar per year.
Modifications to the O-12 were made at the Mathis Shipyard in Camden, NJ. The boat was stripped of military armament and fitted with the latest scientific research equipment. Changes were also made to the superstructure that would allow for operation beneath the ice floes. With the modifications complete, the submarine cast off from Mathis Shipyard on March 16 for the first leg of a journey which would take her to the Brooklyn Navy Yard in New York. Before even leaving the Delaware River, the O-12 was forced to stop at the Philadelphia Navy Yard due to a snowstorm and then stopped at Marcus Hook to take on fuel.
On March 23 the O-12 arrived at the Brooklyn Navy Yard. While entering New York Harbor, the crew suffered the first in a series of accidents and mechanical problems that would plague them on the expedition when Assistant Radio Engineer Willard I. Grimmer fell overboard and drowned. Despite the tragedy, Lady Suzanne Bennett Wilkins (Sir Hubert's wife) christened the submarine the next day using a bottle of ice water, since champagne was unavailable because of prohibition. Among the many spectators was Jean Jules Verne, grandson to the author of 20,000 Leagues Under the Sea, the source of the O-12's new name.
Before setting out on the expedition, the crew put the Nautilus through test runs in various locations off the New England coast. One of the tests included a 90 ft dive off Block Island in Long Island Sound. With mounting criticism from the fact that the expedition was two months behind schedule, it was decided to head out on the first leg of the journey, a planned stop in England. However the bad luck that beset the Nautilus continued. While crossing the Atlantic, the submarine encountered severe storms resulting in severe mechanical failure on June 13 when the starboard engine cracked a cylinder. This was followed by failure of the port engine, probably the result of it being used as the sole source of propulsion.
During the crossing, Wilkins had radioed the submarine's position back to the United States, and after both engines failed the crew broadcast an S.O.S. The Nautilus was eventually rescued on June 15 by the U.S.S. Wyoming (BB-32), which was crossing the Atlantic on a training cruise for midshipmen from the Naval Academy. The Wyoming took the foundering submarine in tow to Queenstown, Ireland. From Queenstown the submarine was towed to Davenport, England for repairs, which were made with considerable delays. Finally, the Nautilus was able to get underway for Bergen, where the scientific officers were brought on board and scientific equipment loaded. One piece of equipment that proved invaluable was the diving chamber, located in the former torpedo room. The chamber could be regulated to match the outside water pressure, allowing scientific equipment to be lowered directly into the water through a hatch.
On August 5, the Nautilus left Bergen headed north in search of the ice floes. The voyage was again repeatedly delayed because of mechanical problems and storms, which further caused the submarine to list at angles of up to 57 degrees. Despite these setbacks, the crew encountered their first ice floe on August 19, and celebrated when Ike Schlossback became the first to step onto the ice at 18:00 hours. For the next few days the Nautilus followed the edge of the ice pack in search of a location to make its first dive attempt. On August 22 the decision was made to dive under the ice floe, but while preparing to submerge it was discovered that the diving rudders were missing, making standard dives impossible. Nevertheless, Wilkins was determined to accomplish some of the planned experiments, particularly those that did not require being submerged. In the course of carrying out the experiments, the opportunity of forcing the Nautilus under an ice pack presented itself on August 31. This was accomplished despite the absence of diving rudders by filing all four ballast tanks and setting the trim at 2.5 degrees. In this way, the Nautilus was able to dive beneath a floe measuring three feet thick and was able to make several additional dives below the ice floes before the voyage ended.
Following a few additional days of research, Wilkins decided it was no longer safe to remain at sea. The Nautilus set course for Longyeartbyen in Svalbard, arriving on September 8. From there, Wilkins planned to proceed to England, but the boat encountered another storm which resulted in further hull damage and engine failure, forcing the Nautilus to dock in Bergen for the last time. After being returned to the United States Navy, the Nautilus was towed out of Bergen and sunk in a Norwegian fjord on November 20, 1931. Ironically, the first ship to cross the north pole was the nuclear submarine U.S.S. Nautilus (SSN - 571) on August 3, 1958.
Blumberg, Frank Arthur O.; Wilkins, George H. (George Hubert), 1888-1958; Arctic regions--Discovery and exploration; Brooklyn Navy Yard; Icebergs; Mathis Shipyard (Camden, N.J.); Nautilus (Submarine); Photoprints; Submarines
- Nautilus (Submarine) Photograph Collection, 1931; 0.5 lin. feet (Box 1)
  - Photographs
    - Nautilus leaving berth at Mathis Shipyard, Camden, NJ, 1931 March 16; 1 (Folder 1)
    - Nautilus on the Delaware River, 1931 March 16; 2
    - Crew members inside control room, 1931March 20; 3
    - Robert D. Shaw in engine room, 1931March 20; 4 (Folder 2)
    - Sloan Danenhower, Jean Jules Verne, and Hubert Wilkins on Nautilus, 1931March 23; 5
    - Christening of Nautilus at Brooklyn Navy Yard, 1931March 23; 6; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of submarine in harbor, with crowd gathered for christening.
    - Crew Photograph, 1931 May 7; 7 (Folder 3)
    - Hubert Wilkins and Lincoln Ellsworth on Nautilus, 1931March 23; 8
    - H. Wilkins and William B. Leeds, 1931March 27; 9
    - Mrs. Harry A. Bruno, H. Wilkins, Elinor Smith, Bernt Balchen and James Fitzmaurice, 1931 May 15; 10 (Folder 4)
    - Frank Blumberg, n.d.; 11
    - Frank Blumberg, n.d.; 12
    - John H. Lunddeck, sitting on hatch, 1931 March 28; 13 (Folder 5)
    - Frank Crilley with Exide battery, n.d.; 14
    - C.E. Johnsted and Sloan Dannenhower, 1931 March 19; 15
    - John H. Lunddeck, 1931 March 28; 16 (Folder 6)
    - Frank Arthur O. Blumberg, 1931 March 28; 17
    - Frank Arthur O. Blumberg, 1931 March 28; 18
    - Group photograph after christening, 1931 March 24; 19 (Folder 7)
    - Isaac Schlossbach exiting hatch, 1931 April 17; 20
    - Clarence P. Holland holding Pennsylvania flag (autographed), 1931 May 28; 21
    - Frank Blumberg looking at gyro, n.d.; 22 (Folder 8)
    - Cornelius P. Royster, John R. Janson and Harry Zoeller in galley, 1931 April 20; 23
    - Frank Crilley exiting air lock, 1931 April 20; 24
    - Frank Crilley and Ray Meyers making radio broadcast from Nautilus, 1931 April 20; 25 (Folder 9)
    - Lt. Cmdr. Edward H. Smith (USCG), 1931 May 19; 26
    - Capt. Wilson Brown (USCG), H. Wilkins and S. Danenhower, 1931 June 4; 27
    - Ike Schlossback and Capt. Wilson Brown, 1931 May 13; 28 (Folder 10)
    - Wilkins waving as Nautilus arrives in Queenstown, Ireland, 1931 June 28; 29
    - Wilkins on deck of Nautilus, 30
    - Nautilus being towed by U.S.S. Wyoming [newspaper clipping], n.d.; 31 (Folder 11)
    - Nautilus being towed into Portsmouth, England, 1931 July 3; 32; 1.0 Photograph(s); View of the submarine being towed.
    - Frank Blumberg inside Nautilus, n.d.; 33
    - Dr. Villinger performing dental operation, 1931 October 2; 34 (Folder 12)
    - Dr. Bernhard Villinger in his office, 1931 April 13; 35
    - Crew members on ice floes, n.d.; 36
    - Nautilus surfaced near ice floes, n.d.; 37; View of submarine surfaced near ice floes. (Folder 13)
    - Nautilus surfaced near ice floes, n.d.; 38
    - Nautilus surfaced near ice floes, n.d.; 39
    - Crew conducting experiments on ice floes, 40 (Folder 14)
    - Edward Clark portrait [autographed], n.d.; 41
    - Frank Crilley portrait [autographed], n.d.; 42
    - Willard J. Grimmer portrait [autographed], n.d.; 43; Signed portrait of Grimmer. (Folder 15)
    - Isaac Schlossback portrait [autographed], n.d.; 44
    - Cornelius P. Royster portrait [autographed], n.d.; 45
    - Frank Blumberg in U.S. Navy uniform, n.d.; 46 (Folder 16)
    - Winter in Norway, postcard, n.d.; 47
    - Winter in Norway, postcard, n.d.; 48
    - Bergen - Floibanen, postcard from Frank Blumberg to Jerry Blumberg, 1931 December 12; 49 (Folder 17)
    - Flaamsdalen, Søgn, postcard, n.d.; 50
    - H. Wilkins in cold weather gear, n.d.; 51; 1.0 Photograph(s); Full length view of Wilkins seated outside wearing cold weather gear.
    - Isaac Schlossback with 3 unknown men, n.d.; 52 (Folder 18)
    - Crew in snow storm with photographers, n.d.; 53
    - Picture of unknown man, n.d.; 54
    - Crewman on bow of Nautilus, n.d.; 55 (Folder 19)
    - Two crewman on bow of Nautilus holding lobsters, n.d.; 56
    - Frank Blumberg in U.S. Navy dress whites, n.d.; 57
    - H. Wilkins receiving Union Jack plague [autographed], n.d.; 58 (Folder 20)
    - Crewman on deck of submarine, 59
    - Two men in-front of car, n.d.; 60
    - Ray E. Meyers, Frank Blumberg, and H. Wilkins in cold weather gear, 61 (Folder 21)
    - Unknown woman, n.d.; 62
    - Group portrait of crew on ice floe., n.d.; 63; 1.0 Photograph(s); Group portrait of crew outside.
    - H. Wilkins and Antonio Salemme inspecting bust, 1930 September 7; 64 (Folder 22)
  - Miscellaneous items
    Scope and Contents note
    Miscellaneous items originally laid into scrapbook
    - Sperryscope newsletter on Nautilus, 1931 April (Folder 23)
    - R.M.S. Berengaria lunch menu, 1931 October 1 (Folder 24)
    - Radiogram Book from expedition [blank pages], n.d. (Folder 25)
  - Scrapbook, Blumberg, Frank Arthur O.
    Scrapbook, now disbound.
    - Scrapbook - Original Layout, n.d. (Folder 26)
    - Scrapbook Page 1 - Magazine clippings, n.d. (Folder 27)
    - Scrapbook Page 2 - Blumberg, Wilkins and Meyers in coldweather gear; Blumberg looking at log (Folder 28)
    - Scrapbook Page 3 - Honorable discharge for Blumberg from Wilkins, 1931 September 12 (Folder 29)
    - Scrapbook Page 4 - Photograph of Frank Blumberg; crew signatures on radiogram page, n.d. (Folder 30)
    - Scrapbook Page 5 - Magazine clippings, n.d. (Folder 31)
    - Scrapbook Page 6 - "Damphools" proclamation, n.d. (Folder 32)
    - Scrapbook Page 7 - Nautilus on cover of Sphere Magazine, n.d. (Folder 33)
    - Scrapbook Page 8 - Magazine clippings, n.d. (Folder 34)
    - Scrapbook Page 9 - Magazine clippings, n.d. (Folder 35)
    - Scrapbook Page 10 - Dixie Holland, portrait [autographed] (Folder 36)
    - Scrapbook Page 11 - Ralph D. Shaw, portrait [autographed], n.d. (Folder 37)